All right, yo, yo, yo, what's up, everybody?
It's Jackson Cook, and I'll be your host today.
I'm the permanent under pod.
Or should I call it the permanent under pee?
Because normally we're three Ps and a pod,
but today it'll just be me.
Chris is visiting his family,
handling some personal issues,
and Tyler's on a beautiful vacation with his family.
So you're stuck with me.
If you're not a huge fan of the J in the pod,
I apologize, but I'm all you got.
It's gonna be a little different today.
I'm gonna cover one topic,
and then we're gonna do a little live vibe coding sesh.
So that'll be interesting,
where I'll build something
that I came up with an idea with last night.
Live and show you guys the end-to-end processes.
Some people have been interested in understanding
how we're editing the pod with just Claude CLI.
So I'm excited to show you guys that.
But first we'll get into our topic of the week.
The only topic we'll be covering,
I shouldn't say we, the only topic I'll be covering,
which is the open AI model escape incident.
So quick overview, if you haven't heard about this,
open AI was benchmarking one of its models
against this benchmark called exploit gem,
and essentially the model escaped,
and went on to infiltrate hugging faces systems
to try to find the answer.
Now, this is a flashy headline AI escaping,
it's guard rails and AI infiltrating
a big name company.
I don't know if hooking face is a company, to be honest.
But, we're gonna dive into each parts,
each step in the process,
and really dig deep here.
So, first up, open AI was testing its model
against a benchmark called exploit gem.
You can think about this as like a test for the AI
to see how good it is.
Very similar to when you were in school
and you were given a test,
and they were trying to see how good you are.
It's similar, but this particular test
is determining how good a model is
at turning a bug into an exploit.
Now, what does that mean?
I thought of a metaphor, I hope that it is relatable.
Basically, if you're at a grocery store
and you identify that there is an exit door
before the checkout line, that is like a bug.
So, you see that there is a exit door
you can go out of and steal the groceries
without paying for them.
Whereas, an exploit would be finding a way
to go out that exit door without getting caught.
Basically, finding a way to take advantage
of the bug and the design of the grocery store.
So, what that means for Exploit Gem is
there are bugs that are built into the test
and then it's up to the model to determine exploits
or ways to access information or execute code
in ways that it shouldn't be able to.
So, basically the model is looking at this test
and it's like, man, I could think about this,
but what if I can get the answer some other way?
So, the model decides I'm going to try
to find the answer somewhere else.
And you have to note that the test is running
in a controlled environment within OpenAI
and it's not supposed to have access to the internet.
But this model found a vulnerability
in the testing environment itself
and was able to utilize that
and then access the open internet.
I think it must be the first time this has happened
otherwise we would have caught it.
Or not we, but OpenAI would have caught it before
and closed the gap.
So, the model escapes through a vulnerability
it finds in the test environment
and then goes onto the open internet
and does research and decides that hugging face
is a good place to look for the answers.
It's the same as if you are sitting in a testing room,
an exam room in your college days
and I don't know, the teacher goes to the bathroom
and you pull out your phone and you're like,
well, I guess I'm gonna go,
I guess nowadays you would go to chat GPT,
but where would you go search for answers before?
Maybe on Chegg, if you were in traditional engineering
and you would ask, hey,
how do you determine the force on this rectangle
and what is the torsion?
So yeah, the model decides I'm going to go to,
kill the mosquito, let's go.
So the model's like, yeah, let's go.
I'm going to hugging face,
it's going to have all the answers.
I don't have to think about nothing.
Only thing I'm thinking about is the easiest way
to get the answers to this test.
But it reaches hugging faces servers
and determines that the answers aren't just
like sitting on the surface.
So it starts prodding hugging faces servers.
And this is where kind of like a robot to robot battle
kind of kicks off where hugging faces team notices
odd behavior on their servers.
So I think their OPSEC, their security team
brings their AI agents and they're like, what's going on?
Why are we getting all these pings?
And it's kind of like the first example
of a bot on bot battle.
You may have heard that people have been saying
for years, especially in the fraud space
that we've been going from like human to human interactions
where the human tries to attack a system
and then the human defends the system
to you have bots driving the attacks.
And the only way to defend against bots or AI
is to have your own AI.
So it's like AI robots battling each other.
Like those old robotic boxing toys,
which I generated a cool video of using Gemini
in case you don't know what these robotic boxing toys
look like 'cause they're kind of old.
So yeah, they were battling the open AI model
that was trying to find the answers.
Open AI claims that the answers were found.
I don't know if that's true or not.
They might just be trying to flex their model,
but it's interesting nonetheless.
And a good effort from the model to avoid doing the work
and to find the answers knowing that it is just a test.
I think that is one of the aspects that researchers
are allegedly are impressed about
is that the agent had the foresight to plan.
Okay, I'm going to go search for the answers in this way.
This is the best path to get a good score on the test.
And then in the aftermath, Hugging Face
wanted to do some pressure testing
and some analysis on their protections in their systems,
but they kept running into guard rails.
This is the same thing we've been talking about
on the podcast with Fable kicking you out
of a Fable session down to a num-dumb Opus session
when it thinks you're doing something naughty.
Hugging Face ran into the same issues,
not just with anthropic models,
but also with open AI models.
So they ended up having to use open source models allegedly.
At first, I think the news was Quinn three,
but I think that the news changed to GLM 5.2.
So the Hugging Face team ended up having to run
on-premises GLM 5.2 to identify
and fix security vulnerabilities,
because every time they tried to identify
and fix security vulnerabilities using anthropic models
such as Fable and Opus or open AI models such as GPT 5.6,
they were getting guard rail.
So another kind of situation where these open source models
have a bit of an advantage 'cause they're less protected
and more or less, more permissive is the right word.
So I think that's also a really interesting aspect.
So the Hugging Face security team ended up using GLM 5.2
to analyze their systems,
even though it may not be as powerful
as the frontier models,
just because it doesn't stop them.
(sighs)
So that's kind of an overview of the, pardon me.
Yeah, so that's the overview
of the open AI Hugging Face model escape incident.
It's not too crazy, really.
It's just that the model,
instead of finding ways to exploit all the bugs
and the test, just decided to exploit
the testing environment itself,
which is kind of funny if you think about it.
Yes, I think it's funny.
So it's very interesting to look at this model
and see how it looks like.
So I think that's what we're gonna look at.
And I think that's what we're gonna look at.
(keyboard clacking)
Oh, yeah.
Two notes on...
Two notes.
You may be wondering, what is Hugging Face?
Hugging Face is
basically NPM or GitHub for AI models.
So it's a place where you can download
open source AI models, open-weight AI models.
For me specifically, I've downloaded stable diffusion,
1.5, 1.6 when I'm generating images locally.
For some of my personal projects,
1.6 does not generate great pictures,
but they're kind of funny.
And also,
yeah, I've downloaded a face image
or like a facial image extraction model
from Hugging Face in the past.
So whenever a company or an individual
decides to release an open source model,
they often will release it on Hugging Face.
And yeah, there's also,
Hugging Face is also a creator of some nice AI libraries
and also maintain popular AI libraries in Python,
like Transformers.
(sighs)
And more recently,
Hugging Face is helping benchmark AI models,
which is probably why the model decided to go there
to look for the answers on the test.
But it's very important in the industry.
If you haven't tried it out,
you should explore some open source models
and see how far behind they are.
One limitation that I've found in open models
is that there aren't any great open source
video generation models.
I think that companies recognize there's a lot of value
and a lot of, I guess, risk for the world
in open source video generation.
For example, Deepfakes,
as you saw on our last podcast, Deepfakes, me, Chris,
and Tyler using a really rudimentary open source model.
That technology has a lot of opportunity for exploitation.
So I can kind of understand companies
not wanting to release it,
but I also think that they don't release
those video generation models
because of monetary reasons.
I think there's a lot of opportunity to make money
generating videos,
whether it be streamlining animation
or making movies without needing to pay actors
or devote the physical time acting things out
and having maybe more fine grain control on the world.
So yeah, who knows if it's ethical or monetary.
I mean, we know it's monetary.
Oh, and one point I wanted to cover from the podcast
last week where I did a benchmark comparison
between Fable and GPT 5.6
on a single medium to medium complexity task.
I said that Fable one shot at it
and the GPT 5.6 had one error.
That was super wrong, actually.
The GPT 5.6 did really, really bad.
It had like one error in the implementation it did,
but it seems like it didn't even grasp the problem
and implemented something much smaller scale
than what I was asking,
even though I gave it to the exact same prompt.
So that just goes to show, I think,
how much better Fable is at like thinking
and understanding the problem space
and researching what already exists.
I think Fable is excellent at working
in these larger code bases.
So that's why it did such a good job,
but it's also an unfair comparison
to just give Fable and GPT 5.6 a single task
to determine their worth, but that's kind of who I am.
And so GPT 5.6 is dead to me.
I will probably never use it, but I'm glad
that I gave it a shot.
I was hoping I would be impressed, but I was not.
Yeah, and just wanted to confirm
because I was kind of hand waving the code review
to Opus 4.8, which might've been biased towards Fable,
but this is the actual truth.
GPT 5.6 did a terrible job.
Sorry, Sam Altman, for your upcoming IPO.
(laughs)
Okay, now we're gonna transition
into a live coding session.
Kind of crazy, but let's be honest.
I've branded myself as the Korean financial
markets expert on the podcast, and while that may be true,
I am the expert on the Korean markets on the pod.
One, I don't know that much
about the Korean financial markets,
and two, we don't really talk about them
because the Korean financial markets,
because Chris, Tyler, and I are mostly interested,
I guess, in the United States as that's where we live.
So my other skillset lies in AI, specifically using it.
So we're gonna do a vibe coding session
where I'm going to build a tool
that will turn my mediocre beatboxing
into something interesting, hopefully.
I have no beatboxing experience at all,
but we're gonna go for it anyways.
All right, see you over there.